ADRIAN DEAN

Tel: 07768 558292 eMail: adean69@aol.com LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/adrian-dean-a1861567/

PROFILE

An Information Technology professional with a varied career spanning more than 20 years in the Financial Services sector. Certified in Amazon Web Services (AWS), a multi-skilled Cloud, Infrastructure and Solution Architect with a strong background in Windows, Linux and z/OS operating platforms, having designed and delivered the IT Infrastructure to support multi-million pound Financial Services business programmes.

SKILLS / ABILITIES

- o AWS (Amazon Web Services) Certified Cloud Practitioner.
- o Extensive Microsoft Windows & z/OS platform knowledge.
- o Large-scale use of VMware technology and virtualisation experience with Linux and Windows servers.
- o 3rd party cloud hosted SaaS solution design and delivery.
- O Identifying and engaging with senior stakeholders, building strong working relationships, capture and translation of key requirements into end to end solution designs.
- o Production of high quality design artefacts and presentation of output to stakeholders / customers, altering communication style and technical content where required to suit the audience.
- Production of project initiation technology cost estimates in support of business case production and approval.
- As part of solution design, production of comprehensive technology delivery cost estimates & quotations.
- o Leadership and direction of multi-disciplined, virtual technical teams in delivery of complex solutions.
- Many years of experience managing complex designs through governance and approval in conformance with IT policy and process.
- Extensive experience working with the following technologies and incorporation into solution designs (not exhaustive):-
 - Microsoft Windows Server (various editions / flavours)
 - VMware ESXi hypervisor
 - RedHat Enterprise Linux, z/OS and z/Linux operating systems
 - Databases (Microsoft SQL, Oracle & IBM DB2)
 - IBM WebSphere platform (WAS, IHS)
 - IBM midrange platform hosting (P Series / Aix)
 - Microsoft SharePoint
 - IBM Tivoli Storage Manager (TSM)
 - 'Qualys' Threat & Vulnerability Management product suite

PERSONAL ATTRIBUTES

- o Adaptable. Able to pick-up new technologies, roles or tasks with ease.
- o Trustworthy, dependable and reliable.
- Strong administrative, communication and listening skills with the ability to establish professional, sustainable and profitable relationships at all levels.
- o Acts with integrity and leads by example.
- o Strong analytical skills, with a desire to constantly challenge and improve existing processes and systems.
- o Pro-active approach to solving problems and delivering new business processes & procedures.
- o Results and quality focussed with an eye for detail.
- o A confident decision maker who embraces change.

EXPERIENCE

JAN 2010 – SEP 2018 INFRASTRUCTURE SOLUTION ARCHITECT, LLOYDS BANKING GROUP PLC.

ACCOUNTABILITIES

- Work with subject matter experts from all application development teams, delivery supply lines and external agencies to collate design input / requirements, and incorporating into IT solutions.
- Using agreed technology patterns and standards, establish appropriate technology set for IT solutions, documenting all architecture / design decisions together with reasoning & justification.
- o Based in West Yorkshire, frequent travel required to London, Edinburgh, Manchester, Bristol and Birmingham (plus satellite locations) as required in line with project / business needs.
- Within each design, incorporate high quality quotations (Capital & Revenue, resources and timescales) that meets business needs.
- Engage with the business at early stages of life cycle and ensure system design takes account of Service Protection principles and IT policy.
- Develop a working relationships and establish a strong 'network' with business areas, application teams and supply lines.

MAJOR HIGHLIGHTS

Delivered Infrastructure and Security designs for circa 20 major bank projects / initiatives over the course of an eight year period, many of which having multi-£M budgets. The main focus of these projects was IT 'currency', addressing issues of software / hardware approaching end of life and losing the support of the associated vendors. Projects were initiated based on the 'risk' associated with the technology being addressed (i.e. probability and impact of an outage) and success was measured in terms of bringing the technology back into a state of ongoing vendor support, thereby mitigating the original risk.

Led the establishment of Infrastructure design principles and processes for the biggest single infrastructure transformation project in the bank's history. This project was scheduled to run for 5+ years with a budget in excess of £20M, with the aim of re-platforming over 3000 business applications onto current / supported IT infrastructure.

Headed up the production of an IT service bid for a major Scottish Insurance company, at a total initial investment cost of circa £7M, and delivered the results on time to very aggressive timescales, presenting the output to the Head of IT.

Investigated the proposed business benefits of a major IT project (Instant Rebuild), being run by a major 3rd party supplier of the bank's IT, and identified that the benefits case was unclear and further, the costs significantly outweighed the potential benefit. I consulted with the head of dept. and recommended that the project's viability be re-assessed. As a direct result the project was closed and circa £150K of expenditure was eliminated.

Demonstrated ability to step outside the boundaries of the day to day role when I voluntarily performed the role of Project Manager for a business project, which required the deployment of a new piece of software to several hundred business users. Upon successful delivery, I presented observations and findings back to my management team and my design peer group, increasing their awareness of daily pressures and challenges facing project managers.

SEP 2002 – DEC 2009 TEST ENVIRONMENT MANAGER, HBOS PLC.

ACCOUNTABILITIES

- o To lead, develop & motivate teams of technical staff, based in disparate locations across the U.K., taking full responsibility for individual and team development and performance management.
- Accountable for the delivery and ongoing support of complex, end-to-end test environments to support the business plans of all bank divisions.
- Working within an agreed financial budget, delivering a measurably better service at a reduced cost, year on year.
- Accountable for the provision of adequate environment support resources, both in terms of numbers and skills, to support the business plans of all bank divisions.

MAJOR HIGHLIGHTS

Led the establishment of risk management processes for the whole of the IT Service division. This required me to, firstly, educate the functions within the division of the basic principles of risk management (what are risks, how to identify, evaluate and categorize them), and secondly to instill good ongoing risk management practices via the introduction of risk logs and regular risk reviews.

Headed up an offshore viability assessment for the whole of the IT Service division (i.e. to understand which services could / should be transferred to our strategic offshore partners). The results of the assessment were presented back to the senior IT leadership team who, upon my recommendation, agreed that the offshore strategy should remain unchanged for the foreseeable future.

Headed up the establishment of 'Sarbanes-Oxley' compliance processes for the Service Introduction function.

Led the merger of two Edinburgh based support teams, consisting of similar roles and responsibilities, into a single unit, resulting in a 50% cost saving to the business with no reduction in service levels.

SEP 1996 – AUG 2002 WINDOWS SERVER BACKUP/RECOVERY SME, HALIFAX PLC

ACCOUNTABILITIES

- Accountable for the backup (and recovery where required) of distributed servers & data across the entire bank distributed network.
- o Accountable for the archive and data retention of specific distributed data for legal and regulatory purposes.
- Accountable for the leadership, development & motivation of a team of technical staff, taking full responsibility for individual and team development and performance management.

MAJOR HIGHLIGHTS

Developed and implemented a TSM (Tivoli Storage Manager) backup & recovery solution for the 'branch' network, involving backup of key information from servers located in every branch, across the entire UK, and bringing that data back over the wide area network for secure storage within the West Yorkshire based data centres.

Implemented an archival solution for the branch network, using the TSM infrastructure previously delivered to facilitate server backup & recovery, to enable journal information to be retained for a regulatory period of seven years.

Designed a delivered a 'local' backup and recovery solution for seven 'Business Centres' located in various UK locations, backing up servers / data to an on-site tape storage device.

Was accredited as an IBM Certified Professional in Tivoli Storage Manager, having sat and passed the necessary examination, becoming the first non-IBM employee in the UK to achieve such accreditation.

INDUSTRY QUALIFICATIONS

DECEMBER 2018

CERTIFIED CLOUD PRACTITIONER, AMAZON WEB SERVICES (AWS)

Embarked on Amazon Web Services (AWS) cloud training program, training for certified Solutions Architect – Associate, sat and passed "Certified Cloud Practitioner" examination.

NOVEMBER 2016

INFORMATION SECURITY, BRITISH COMPUTER SOCIETY (BCS)

Subsequent to a week-long training course entitled "Certificate in Information Security Management Principles", sat an examination and attained a **distinction**.

DECEMBER 2014

SOLUTION ARCHITECTURE, BRITISH COMPUTER SOCIETY (BCS)

Subsequent to a week-long training course entitled "Intermediate Certificate in Enterprise and Solution Architecture", sat an examination and attained a **pass**.

MAY 1999

IBM CERTIFIED TSM PROFESSIONAL, IBM CORPORATION

Sat an examination entitled "IBM Certified Professional - Tivoli Storage Manager" and attained a <u>pass</u>, becoming the first non-IBM employee in the UK to achieve this qualification.

EDUCATION

1980 - 1987

A LEVEL QUALIFICATIONS, HALIFAX CATHOLIC HIGH SCHOOL

Attained 'A Level' qualifications in Computer Studies, Mathematics and Physics.